Guide to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Films. ALBA FILM 001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Films.
1938-2003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA FILM 001
3.25 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 1 manuscript box.
Collection consists of films, videos, and DVDs on the Spanish Civil War, the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, and Spanish Republican refugees, including a 1938 documentary short directed by Henri Cartier –Bresson, "With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain"; footage shot by Harry Randall, member of the Lincoln Brigade itself, in 1937-1938; a 1939 documentary film directed by Jean-Paul Le Chanois (aka Jean-Paul Dreyfuss) entitled "Refuge," about exiled Spanish Republicans in French refugee camps; and an episode from a 1978 television documentary series on the Spanish Civil War.
Scope and Contents Note
The materials consist of 16mm films, videotapes in various formats, and DVDs collected by the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives on the subjects of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and the Spanish Civil War. They include film footage shot in Spain ca.1937-1938 by Harry Randall for the Photographic Unit of the Fifteenth International Brigade; an 18-minute 1937 documentary entitled "With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain," produced by Herbert Kline, directed by Henri Cartier-Bresson, and shot by Cartier-Bresson and Jaques Lemare; "Refuge," (1939) a 27-minute documentary film about exiled Spanish Republicans in refugee camps in France that was directed by Jean-Paul Le Chanois (aka Jean-Paul Dreyfus) and combines newsreels and original footage (including sequences shot with a hidden camera); and an episode of a 1978 television documentary series "Between the Wars: The Spanish Civil War," hosted by journalist Eric Sevareid.
The footage shot by Randall includes soldiers (presumably Abraham Lincoln Brigade members and possibly Spanish soldiers as well) at the front and behind the front lines, marching, training, and relaxing, Spanish peasants planting, and scenes of war-caused destruction. "With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain" documents Brigade members in Spain, training near the front, waiting to be mobilized, wounded, and at hospitals. It includes close-ups of Brigade members, the nurses who treated them, and local residents Brigaders met while recovering from their wounds, as well as scenes of Madrid during the fall of 1937, and a soccer game in Benicassim.
Access Restrictions
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Existence and Location of Copies
"With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain Film Collection" (FILM 014) at the Tamiment Library, contains essentially the same film as "With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain" in this collection; a reference DVD of the same in FILM 014 may be screened for reference purposes. Other films and videos in this collection may also contain parts or versions of "With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain," but absent a thorough screening it is not possible to know for certain.
Custodial History
The materials in this collection were acquired by the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA)—a non-profit organization devoted to preserving the memory of the volunteers who fought against fascism and to defend the Spanish Republic during the Spanish Civil War. ALBA first donated a low-resolution VHS tape of a video transfer of 16mm footage shot by Harry Randall, a member of the Lincoln Brigade, in 1937-1938 (the Library created a screening copy of this VHS); ALBA then donated the balance of the materials to the Tamiment Library in 2009.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged in three series.
Series I. Films.
Series II. Videotapes.
Series III. DVDs.
Related Archival Materials
"With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain" Film (FILM.014).
Harry Randall: Fifteenth International Brigade Films and Photographs (ALBA PHOTO 011)
Biographical/Historical Note
The Spanish Civil War (1936 – 1939) was a conflict between the newly-elected left-leaning government of the Spanish Republic and its supporters and the (ultimately successful) rebellion against the Republic led by General Francisco Franco and supported by Hitler and Mussolini. Thousands of men and women from around the world volunteered to serve as soldiers and medical and support personnel for the Republic, which organized them into International Brigades (including the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, made up of North Americans). Film was one of the weapons used by international organizations supporting the Republic and the Brigades to document the war and to generate support and raise money; after the war they used moving images to aid the Republic's refugees.
The major works in the collection include "With the Lincoln Brigade In Spain", directed by Henri Cartier-Bresson; footage shot by in Spain ca.1937-1938, by Harry Randall, head of the Photographic Unit of the Fifteenth International Brigade (which functioned as the photographic arm of the Lincoln Brigade); and "Refuge."
"With the Lincoln Brigade In Spain," is a short documentary film produced by Herbert Kline, directed by still photographer Henri Cartier-Bresson, and shot in 35mm (although distributed in 16 mm) by Cartier-Bresson and movie camera operator Jaques Lemare. It was filmed in 1937 and released in 1938. Shown in union halls, clubs, and other small venues throughout the United States, "With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain" was used to raise funds to bring the Brigaders home. (At the same time that it was shooting "With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain," the same production team was shooting another Lincoln Brigade-related documentary film in Spain--"Return to Life"--for the American Medical Bureau of the North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy in Spain (AMB)). "Refuge," was shot in 1939, to publicize the plight of Spanish Republican refugees in refugee camps in France and the deplorable conditions in these camps. It was produced by Cine Liberte and the AMB, directed by Jean-Paul Le Chanois (aka Jean-Paul Dreyfuss), and edited by Irving Lerner. It includes footage from (and may be a shortened version of) "Un peuple attend," another documentary on the same subject shot earlier that year, and also directed by Le Chanois.
• Crusells, Magí."REFUGE, a pro-republican documentary from the Spanish Civil War." International Journal of Iberian Studies 19 (2006): 231-239. Accessed July 3, 2012. doi: 10.1386/ijis.19.3.231_3.
• Faber, Sebastiaan. "Images of Displacement -- The Spanish Civil War and the Birth of the Modern Refugee." The Volunteer 16 (2009): 6-9; 17-18. Accessed July 3, 2012. http://www.oberlin.edu/faculty/sfaber/refugee.pdf
• Randall, Harry, interview by Erika Gottfried. April 10, 2002. New York, New York. Harry W. Randall, Jr. Oral History Interview (transcript). Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Vertical Files: Individuals. Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, New York, New York.
• Rosemont, Franklin. "Spanish Revolution of 1936." In The Encyclopedia of the American Left, Second Edition. Eds. Mari Jo Buhle, Paul Buhle, and Dan Georgakas. New York: Oxford University Press, 1998. 792-793.
• Salas, Juan. "Henri Cartier-Bresson Film Found in ALBA Archive." The Volunteer 17 (2010): 8-9,11. Accessed July 3, 2012. http://www.albavolunteer.org/2010/03/henri-cartier-bresson-footage-%E2%80%A8found-in-alba-archive/
• Sills, Sam. "Abraham Lincoln Brigade." In The Encyclopedia of the American Left, Second Edition. Eds.Mari Jo Buhle, Paul Buhle, and Dan Georgakas. New York: Oxford University Press, 1998. 2-4.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some moving image materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing only. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information, to request digitization of materials, and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Videocassettes.; 16mm; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Videotapes.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Sources.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Barcelona (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Refugees.; Television journalists.; Television programs.; Motion pictures.; Documentary films; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Archives; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Le Chanois, Jean-Paul, 1905-1985; Cartier-Bresson, Henri, 1908-2004; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Randall, Harry W., Jr., 1915-; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV. Photographic Unit; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Dreyfuss, Jean-Paul, 1905-1985; Sevareid, Eric, 1912-1992
- Films., undated
  - With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, Reel 1., undated (Reel 1)
  - Between the Wars: The Spanish Civil War., undated (Reel 2)
  - With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, Reels 1 & 2., undated (Reel 3)
  - Refuge., undated (Reel 4)
  - Holographic Lincoln Brigade., undated (Reel 5)
  - Otro Crimen de Franco., undated (Reel 6)
  - NYU "With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain" 16mm tinted master positive R. 1 (of 2)., undated (Reel 7)
  - Tam/Wag With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, Reel 2., undated (Reel 8)
  - [Unlabeled]., undated (Reel 9)
  - Unlabeled film fragment, undated (Box 5)
- Videotapes., 1938 - 1948
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" [VHS]., May 29, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 1)
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archival; 1. Film (MOS) Lincoln Brigade 24:00; 2. Spanish Civil War (Spanish Audio); Cuban Film 1948; [SOMETIMES CALLED "BENE CASIM"]" [VHS]., Apr. 24, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 2)
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" [2] [VHS]., May 23, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 3)
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archive; Spanish Civil War Footage; 28 min (audio in English); 24 min (MOS); 11 min (audio in Spanish).", undated (Box 2, Cassette 4)
  - Spanish Civil War Harry Randall Footage Circa 37-38 Benicasim [Digibeta, Transfer]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 5: [31142050279523])
  - "Spanish Civil War" Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer @ 12fps Harry Randall Film Spain 1937-38 Master [Digibeta "Film Transfer"]., 1997 (Box 2, Cassette 6: [31142050279580])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Spanish Civil War with Spanish Audio Cuban film 1948 [Digibeta, "Clone"]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 7: [31142050279564])
  - "Spanish Civil War" Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer & 12fps Harry Randall Film Spain 1937-38 [Digibeta, "Clone"]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 8: [31142050279598])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade [BetaSP]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 9: [31142050279689])
  - Spanish Civil War Refuge (Audio in English) [Digibeta, "Clone"]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 10: [31142050279648])
  - "Benicasim" "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical [Digibeta, "Clone"]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 11: [31142050279739])
  - "Benicasim" "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical [Digibeta, "Dub Master"]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 12: [31142050279747])
  - "Spanish Civil War" Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer @ 12fps Harry Randall Film Spain 37-38 Master [Digibeta, "Film Transfer"]., Oct. 9, 1997 (Box 2, Cassette 13: [31142050279663])
  - Spanish Civil War [BetaSP]., Feb. 20, 2001 (Box 2, Cassette 14: [31142050279705])
  - "Spanish Civil War" Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer @ 12fps [Digibeta, "Clone"]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 15: [31142050279713])
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" [Digibeta, "Clone"]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 16: [31142050279697 ])
  - George Sossenko's Trip to Spain April '97 [VHS]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 17: [31142050279754])
  - VALB Tape [VHS]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 18: [31142050279770])
  - The Big Picture #12: The Abraham Lincoln Brigade [BetaSP]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 19: [31142050279671])
  - "You Are History, You are Legend" The Legacy of the International Brigades [VHS]., undated (Box 2, Cassette 20: [31142050279788])
  - Their Cause Was Liberty Sample Material [VHS]., Mov. 6, 1992 (Box 2, Cassette 21: [31142050279630])
  - "Spanish Civil War" 16mm Transfer @ 12fps [VHS, "Dub"]., Oct. 10, 1997 (Box 2, Cassette 22: [31142050279762])
  - In Search of the Lincoln Brigade Demo [VHS]., 1999 (Box 2, Cassette 23: [31142050279655])
  - "Spanish Civil War" Harry Randall Film Spain 1937-38 Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer @ 12fps [VHS]., Apr. 24, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 24: [31142050279721])
  - [Harry Randall Film - Dub of video dub of 16mm footage shot by Harry Randall, head of the 15th International Brigade's Photographic Unit, in fall/winter 1937], undated (Box 003, Cassette 34)
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" [Digibeta, "Film Transfer"]., May 29, 2003 (Box 003, Cassette 25: [31142050279606])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade (sometimes called "Benecasim"), Spanish Civil War (Spanish Audio) Cuban film 1948 [Digibeta, "Master"]., Dec. 16, 1996 (Box 003, Cassette 26: [31142050279531])
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" [Digibeta, "Clone"]., May 29, 2003 (Box 003, Cassette 27: [31142050279614])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Spanish Civil War (Audio in English) [Digibeta, "Master"]., Dec. 16, 1996 (Box 003, Cassette 28: [31142050279572])
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade 64th Anniversary Reunion [Digibeta, "Master"]., Sep. 15, 2001 (Box 003, Cassette 29: [31142050279622])
  - Harry Randall Film "Spanish Civil War" [BetaSP]., undated (Box 003, Cassette 30: [31142050279556])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade (sometimes called "Benecasim"), Spanish Civil War (Spanish Audio) Cuban film 1948 [BetaSP]., Nov. 13, 1998 (Box 003, Cassette 31: [31142050279549])
  - Spanish Civil War Refuge (Audio in English) [DCT, "Film Transfer"]., undated (Box 003, Cassette 32: [31142050279804])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archival Film, Spanish Civil War (Audio in Spanish) [DCT, "Film Transfer"]., Dec. 14, 1996 (Box 003, Cassette 33: [31142050279796])
  - Harvard/MIT Conference, "The Spanish Civil War: the Aftermath", 1986-10-16-1986-10-18 (Box 5, Cassette 35-46)
  - Pete Seeger, Abraham Lincoln Brigade event, 2005-05-01 (Box 5, Cassette 47-49)
  - Noticiario de Laya Films no. 3, 2007-05-02 (Box 5, Cassette 50)
- DVDs.
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archival 'Film (MOS)' TRT 24:00.", Jan. 30, 1997 (Dvd 1, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - [Harry Randall Film - DVD dub from VHS dub of 16mm footage shot by Harry Randall, head of the 15th International Brigade's Photographic Unit, in fall/winter 1937], undated (Video 4, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - "Brandeis VHS Dub 'Benicasim' 'Abraham Lincoln Brigade' 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical 24 & 18 fps TRT: 19:00" [Copy 1]., Jan. 29, 1997 (Dvd 2, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - "Brandeis VHS Dub 'Benicasim' 'Abraham Lincoln Brigade' 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical 24 & 18 fps TRT: 19:00" [Copy 2]., Jan. 29, 1997 (Dvd 3, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - "Brandeis VHS Dub 'Benicasim' 'Abraham Lincoln Brigade' 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical 24 & 18 fps TRT: 19:00" [Copy 3]., Jan. 29, 1997 (Dvd 4, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - "Dreams and Nightmares: a Personal Memoir of the Spanish Civil War." A film by Abe Osheroff, 1975 (Box 5, Dvd 5)
  - ALBA: Archive of Activism, 2004 (Box 5, Dvd 6)
  - International Brigades Memorial Trust annual meeting, with Ruth Frow, 2006 (Box 5, Dvd 7)
  - un pessic de memoria al Priorat ("A Pinch of Priorat Memories"), Produced by No jubilem la memoria, 2006 (Box 5, Dvd 8-9)